Xincheng Huang

Phone: 734-263-4841 | Email: xchuang@cs.ubc.ca | Website: https://xincheng.me

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My current research focuses on bridging the physical and virtual worlds in remote AR/VR collaboration. From sharing a slice of physical surfaces to fully immersive environments, I hope my endeavor will make future telepresence and remote collaboration more seamless and natural. My research along this target has led to publications to IMWUT, TVCG, and UIST.

EDUCATION

University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC

Sept 2021 – present

Ph.D. in Computer Science *Advisor: Dr. Robert Xiao*

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

Aug 2019 – April 2021

M.S. in Computer Science and Engineering

Advisors: Dr. Nikola Banovic and Dr. Alanson Sample

New York University Shanghai, Shanghai, China

Aug 2015 – May 2019

B.S. with double major in Computer Science and Interactive Media Arts

Graduated with Magna Cum Laude

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant. University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC

Sept 2021 - present

X Lab. Advised by Dr. Robert Xiao

Enhancing the multi-modal interactivity of remote shared experience in AR/VR. So far, I have explored physical surface sharing and ad-hoc virtual replica creation for remote MR collaboration [J3], and 360° Video VR telepresence with 5G millimeter wave and multi-access edge computing [J2].

Research Assistant. University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

Mar 2020 – April 2021

Computational HCI Lab. Advised by Dr. Nikola Banovic and Dr. Alanson Sample

Conducted a research project as the first author on inferring assembly structures from user behaviors [J1]. This work utilized UHF-RFID sensing to profile the movement data of building blocks during assembly tasks, and then inferred the structures being built in real-time given the movement profile with Markov Chain Monte Carlo.

Research Assistant. University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

Jan 2020 – April 2020, Jan 2021 – April 2021

Secure Cloud Manufacturing Group. Advised by Dr. Kira Barton

Created an educational Virtual Manufacture Space in VR for the Detroit Area Pre-college Engineering Program (DAPCEP). Presented two iterations of the project, based on VR and WebGL, on DAPCEP 2020 and DAPCEP 2021.

Undergraduate Research Assistant. New York University, New York City, NY

Jan 2018 – Dec 2018

New York University – Guggenheim. Conserving Computer-based Art Initiative. Advised by Prof Deena Engel Conducted code analysis for a software-based art: Color Panel, by John F. Simon Jr. 1998. Compiled the results of code analysis and suggestions for conservation in a 20-page report archived by the Guggenheim Museum.

PUBLICATIONS

- [C1] Xincheng Huang*, Michael Yin*, Ziyi Xia, Robert Xiao. 2024. VirtualNexus: Enhancing 360-Degree Video AR/VR Collaboration with Environment Cutouts and Virtual Replicas. In *The 37th Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST '24), October 13–16, 2024, Pittsburgh, PA, USA*. ACM, New York, NY, USA, 12 pages. (To appear. Access preprint here)
- [J3] Xincheng Huang and Robert Xiao. 2023. SurfShare: Lightweight Spatially Consistent Physical Surface and Virtual Replica Sharing with Head-mounted Mixed-Reality. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 7, 4, Article 162 (December 2023), 24 pages. https://doi.org/10.1145/3631418.
- [J2] <u>Xincheng Huang</u>, James Riddell, and Robert Xiao. 2023. "Virtual Reality Telepresence: 360-Degree Video Streaming with Edge-Compute Assisted Static Foveated Compression", in *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics*, doi: 10.1109/TVCG.2023.3320255.
- [J1] Xincheng Huang, Keylonnie L. Miller, Alanson P. Sample, and Nikola Banovic. 2023. StructureSense: Inferring Constructive Assembly Structures from User Behaviors. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 6, 4, Article 204 (December 2022), 25 pages. https://doi.org/10.1145/3570343.
- [T2] Zhanghao Chen*, <u>Xincheng Huang</u>*. 2019. 3D Point Cloud Registration Algorithms for the Telewindow. Undergraduate thesis for Computer Science at New York University Shanghai. Advised by Dr. Olivier Marin and Prof. Michael Naimark.
- [T1] <u>Xincheng Huang</u>. 2019. Immersive Strategies: A First-Person Perspective Chess Game in VR. Undergraduate thesis for Interactive Media Arts at New York University Shanghai. Advised by Dr. Alison De Fren.

(*: equal contribution)

TEACHING AND MENTORING

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Sept 2022 – Dec 2022

University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC

CPSC 554X – Machine Learning and Signal Processing. Duties: grading and responding to student questions.

Learning Assistant

Feb 2019 – May 2019

New York University Shanghai, Shanghai, China

CSCI-SHU 101 Introduction to Computer Science. Duties: holding tutoring office hours, conducting review sessions, and facilitating class activities. Received award for "Excellent Tutoring" and "Most Appointed Office Hour".

Undergraduate Mentoring

Dieter Frehlich, undergraduate student at University of British Columbia

Junkai (Kelvin) Ding, undergraduate student at University of British Columbia

James Riddell, undergraduate student at *University of British Columbia*, then M.S. at *University of Waterloo* Keylonnie Miller, undergraduate student at *University of Michigan*, then *Facebook*

ACADEMIC SERVICE

Reviewed 11 papers in various journals and conferences:

SUI 2024, VRST 2024, CHI Play 2024, IMWUT 2024, ISMAR 2024, CHI 2024, UIST 2023, CHI 2023

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Assistant Software Engineer, PwC Service Deliver Center, Shanghai

July 2018 - Oct 2018

SAP Department. Developed SAP-based APIs for financial reports, material, and storage management using ABAP and OpenSQL.

AWARDS

MITACS Accelerate 2023-2024

Conducting Project *Rich, Immersive AR/VR communication* in collaboration with *Rogers Communications Canada Inc.* with a Mitacs Accelerate award with 60000 CAD.

Latin Award, Magna Cum Laude, New York University Shanghai

2019

Awarded to top 15% of the graduated class

Dean's List for Academic Year, NYU Shanghai

2015 - 2016, 2016 - 2017, 2017 - 2018, 2018 - 2019

Awarded to top 30% for each academic year

University Recognition Award, NYU Shanghai

2017 - 2018

LEADERSHIP

ENACTUS NYU Shanghai, Vice President

2016 - 2017

Led the NYU Shanghai's branch of <u>ENACTUS</u>, a world-wide social entrepreneurial student organization. Participated in the user interviews, product design, and prototyping for our project: "A Third Eye: A Digital Blind Crutch". Won the *First prize* and the *Best technology innovation* award in ENACTUS social innovation competition of East China, and an 80000 CNY (~12000 USD) grant from the Chinese Charity Association (Shenzhen).